<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hustlin | Data, Science, Startups and Investment]]></title>
  <link href="http://davidcoallier.com//blog/categories/hustlin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://davidcoallier.com//"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T04:13:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://davidcoallier.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Coallier]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Quantitative Entrepreneur]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidcoallier.com//the-quantitative-entrepreneur"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T01:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidcoallier.com//the-quantitative-entrepreneur</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>Earlier this week, <a href="http://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a> published an article about
<a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/06/01/the-quantitative-vc/"><strong>The Quantitative VC</strong></a> and how investment firms are increasingly using data to validate investments. </p>

<p>Allow me to display some tools and algorithms <strong>entrepreneurs</strong> can build and use to find and focus on relevant investors.</p>

<h2 id="the-role-of-an-angel">The Role of an Angel</h2>

<p>It is widely known that some investors are analytic, some are strategic, and some are
plainly emotional investors. I will leave the emotional investors out of this post, and despite how I fail to understand
them and the rationale behind their investment strategies, I also see the obvious value they bring to many startups.</p>

<p>As a <em>cherub</em> strategic angel investor and startup advisor, I always try to find creative ways to 
help startups try and find investments (<em>if they</em> <strong>absolutely</strong> <em>need it</em>). This task usually modestly begins by making connections to relevant venture capitalists, 
accelerators, incubators, and friends rather than <em>only</em> giving my opinions on the product. There’s a lot of VERY good experienced investors and advisors out there, and
often times I believe startups might benefit a lot more by getting in touch with more experienced, more appropriate investors directly.</p>

<p>Simply explained: <em>I put people more intelligent than me in touch with other more intelligent people</em>.</p>

<p>Despite all the introductions an angel can make, on numerous occasions, entrepreneurs and general startup people just have to go out there and make connections. This
is known as the <em>cringeworthy</em> term: <strong>networking</strong>. Go out there and do it.</p>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/msuster">Mark Suster</a> wrote a blog post entitled <a href="http://www.bothsidesofthetable.com/2013/05/27/8-tips-to-get-the-most-out-of-your-investors-and-board/">8 tips to get the most out of your investors and board</a>. </p>

<p>In the post, he mentionned a very important quote by Rob Bailey the CEO of <a href="http://datasift.com/">DataSift</a>, a quote that resonated deeply with me:</p>

<pre><code>Spend time building investor relationship long before you raise money.
</code></pre>

<p>To an average entrepreneur, this quote seems evident, but also utopic. <em>Who do you build a relationship with? How do you decide? How do you maximise your chances whilst minimising the amount of energy/time doing it? Who’s really influential, who can make the bridges to other investors? How do I pin-point investors relevant to my industry?</em></p>

<p>This is where the <em>strategic</em> part of the angel-investor comes in. Entrepreneurs are often standing so close to the trees that they fail to see the forest. It is the job of the
early-stage investors to take a step-back, relax, and provide objective insight. At this point, <em>data becomes important</em>.</p>

<h2 id="strategically-not-being-vexatious">Strategically Not Being Vexatious</h2>

<p>The gig is remarkably straight-forward. Early stage investors have to attempt to not worry, annoy, and disturb the startups when the timing is wrong. <em>Don’t get me wrong, I love nothing more than shaking up startups when the timing is right</em>. I’ve miserably chosen my timing on numerous occasions which brought me, as a person and investor to extensively understand the value of <strong>good timing</strong>… thankfully we are learning beings :-)).</p>

<p>In an attempt to make the entrepreneurial and investment worlds more connected I’ve developed many <strong>personal</strong> products that allow me to analyse startups and whether or not people seem to be interested, if the future (<em>I just said future. Yes</em>) appears bleak or promising, and what the ecosystem of the industry of the startup receiving the investment seems receptive. This includes a mix of natural language processing, statistical analysis, backtesting analysis, acquisition potential analysis, etc. </p>

<p>These are fairly standard (I hope) tools for most investors attempting to maximise their returns. </p>

<p>Here’s the kick: <strong>Entrepreneurs also have to analyse investors</strong>. For entrepreneurs, building relationships and doing your own due-dilligence on potential investors is primordial. There is no extent to the importance of stressing that fact with entrepreneurs.</p>

<h2 id="analyse-the-investors">Analyse the Investors</h2>

<p>Being interested and involved into investments and advising startups, I often see entrepreneurs who <strong>see</strong> the value of public and open data but rarely notice startups leveraging the power of that data to strategically focus their efforts when building their network.</p>

<p><strong>What if you could know which investor is likely to make more bridges, which one is the most influential, or simply which one has the most connections for the industry in which you operate?</strong>. As an entrepreneur, this sort of information is extremely relevant as it saves you time and energy. It allows you to work on growing your business, your team, your product.</p>

<p>Turns out, there’s quite a bit of information out there. It’s easy to see which prominent investors are switching their strategies in early-stage startups, it’s unchallenging to see which investors are friends with others (<em>cliques</em>), which industries they are targeting, etc.</p>

<h2 id="the-experiment-which-investors">The Experiment, Which Investors?</h2>

<p>On rare occasions will I show my boring investment work, but sometimes it’s worth showing so that entrepreneurs understand the value in the point I’m trying to get across (<em>Considering that each language I speak looks like my fifth language</em>).</p>

<p>After having parsed and retrieved the information (management, investments, investors, etc.) of over <strong>140,000</strong> businesses from the <a href="http://developer.crunchbase.com">CrunchBase API</a>, I’ve borrowed <em>centrality measuring</em> techniques from the field known as graph theory to identify influential investors as well as investors more likely to make bridges to others. </p>

<p>Take <a href="http://davidcoallier.com/experiments/important-investors">a look at the results of influential/bridging investors per industry</a></p>

<h2 id="sparse-and-limited-results">Sparse and Limited Results</h2>

<p>Now, magicians do not always (<em>almost never in fact</em>) reveal their tricks. You can consider this post a <em>reminder for entrepreneurs</em> that data, mathematics, and pragmatism are powerful tools when used together intelligently. </p>

<p>What the experiment fails to show are trends, cliques, behavioural changes in investors and investor-cliques, average investment per investor, etc. Most of that information is available to you through online sources, and it is extremely easy to analyse ;-) <strong>e.g.: One does not require a PhD in mathematical statistics in order to be able to perform powerful analyses</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="relevant-and-important-investors-per-sector">Relevant and Important Investors Per Sector</h2>

<p>As noted above, you can find the <a href="http://davidcoallier.com/experiments/important-investors">visual representation of the experiment here</a> .</p>

<h2 id="about-investor-introductions">About Investor Introductions</h2>

<p>Now, don’t go sending emails to all the top investors in your industry. All those new ideas you’ve just acquired from the post, put them aside and reflect on the following (Especially the currency part):</p>

<p>Not unlike <a href="http://www.bothsidesofthetable.com/2012/03/21/why-you-should-think-twice-before-you-send-that-intro-email/">Mark Suster</a> I truly believe that introductions are <em>the currency of mavens</em> and that each introduction should be carefully planned, and be respectful of the receiving investor. </p>

<p>Mark makes a point that an investor should know the individual whom he is introducing well enough to vouch for the likelihood that their product is of high-quality. </p>

<p>I sometimes make introductions for other angel investor friends of mine interested in my network and vice-versa, therefore I am  slightly in disagreement with Marks’ point about knowing and vouching the person and their products. </p>

<p>Often times, knowing the other angel (The other angel requesting an intro into your network) well enough is a sufficient  judge of character metric. I <em>trust</em> them and they wouldn’t ask me to introduce a company they invested in if the product was sub-par. </p>

<p>When an entrepreneur takes an angel on board, the introductions made by that angel should be relevant to both the investors and the startup. Remember, this is a surprisingly small world (An analysis of the data mentioned above would clearly show you).</p>

<p>Entrepreneurs, keep in mind that the timing of an introduction is <em>extremely</em> important as well. Look at the investments history, look at how investors being introduced behave, and do your research about them. <em>Take your time</em> and <em>plan carefuly</em>; The intro you asked your angel to make might be the last you’ll ever need to ask.</p>

<p>Do not be afraid to tell your angels and advisors to back off if you aren’t pleased with them or you aren’t ready for certain intros. You are in a relationship after all. </p>

<h2 id="closing-note-for-entrepreneurs">Closing Note For Entrepreneurs</h2>

<p>The sheer amount of self-proclaimed investors (<em>not unlike myself</em>) and borderline mediocre angel investors 
is increasing with every acquisition, public offering, and vested share scheme. </p>

<p>It seems like a trend to see individuals from the <strong>tech</strong> scene sell their company or cash-in their stock schemes
 and simply turn to angel investing, without fully understanding the risks but more importantly without understanding the seriousness of the role they will play in many startups they’ll invest in.</p>

<p>Moreover, <em>raising money and selling a company does not inherently make you a good investor</em>. For an entrepreneur, a bad 
investor (Who joins at an early stage), or even a one-trick-poney-advisor can be quite detrimental and exhausting.</p>

<p>As an <strong>entrepreneur</strong>, please carefully choose who you bring on board as an investor, and/or advisor.</p>

<h2 id="closing-note-for-investors">Closing Note For Investors</h2>

<p>Get your shit together. Don’t be an ass, be present when they need it, take the time to talk to them, but more importantly, <strong>be level-headed, objective and honest</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>

<p>The fact that I did not reach the results of my own experiment should show that I did not rig the results. Having been a struggling entrepreneur many times, my sole purpose 
as an investor/advisor is to get more startups to <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/05/04/bootstrapping-forever/">bootstrap</a> their companies
as much as possible, and help people connect together. </p>

<p>As an individual on a perpetual quest to connect intelligent people together, leveraging technology and data to derive creative insight for both the investment and entrepreneurial world is my only motivation. </p>

<p>I really want our daughters and sons to be proud of the era they live in, and this is only going to be possible if amazing things happen. Startups make amazing things, investors can help them realise them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
